<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Desert Defender devlog</title>
    <link>https://blog.desert-defender.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Desert Defender devlog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.desert-defender.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>24 - Gameplay Framework, Instance, Save, Mode and other stuff</title>
      <link>https://blog.desert-defender.com/posts/24---gameplay-framework-instance-save-mode-and-other-stuff/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.desert-defender.com/posts/24---gameplay-framework-instance-save-mode-and-other-stuff/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I wanted to go back to the game loop logic and introduce a &lt;code&gt;PlayerScore&lt;/code&gt;, basically the nomber of snakes killed, and, &lt;code&gt;PlayersCoins&lt;/code&gt;, coins system for upgrading weapons, buying pickups and so on. But soon I had a problem of understanding: which class should handle what? How do I update the HUD values? Which class modifies what?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I took couple of days to read some documentation, read articles, watch tutorials. Here is the list of sources I found useful in my quest to master the Unreal Gameplay Framework:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>23 - Smooth camera transitions between character states</title>
      <link>https://blog.desert-defender.com/posts/23---smooth-camera-transitions-between-character-states/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.desert-defender.com/posts/23---smooth-camera-transitions-between-character-states/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today I spend few hours to fix camera transitions. Previously, I have established three lengths for the character camera arm based on if the character is unequipped, equipped or equipped and aiming. I was changing those values in the &lt;code&gt;Equip&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;HideOrShowEquippedWeapon&lt;/code&gt; functions of the &lt;code&gt;CombatComponent&lt;/code&gt;. Also, I was just setting those values without transition resulting in a shaky gameplay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To fix this, and to have my camera code in one place, I created a &lt;code&gt;InterpCameraArmLength&lt;/code&gt; function using &lt;code&gt;FInterpTo&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;DeltaTime&lt;/code&gt;. The function is called in the &lt;code&gt;TickComponent&lt;/code&gt; an changes camera arm length continuously.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>22 - GameMode logic, win or defeat, score and UI</title>
      <link>https://blog.desert-defender.com/posts/22---gamemode-logic-win-or-defeat-score-and-ui/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.desert-defender.com/posts/22---gamemode-logic-win-or-defeat-score-and-ui/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After my detour through the weapon actions, I returned to the game loop logic. I started by creating a &lt;code&gt;DesertDefenderGameMode&lt;/code&gt; class and used it for the TinyTown level. I added four functions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;ActivateSpawners()&lt;/code&gt;, called from &lt;code&gt;PostLogin()&lt;/code&gt;, to manage &lt;code&gt;SpawnPoints&lt;/code&gt; and introduce a warmup delay before starting fight snakes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;PlayerEliminated()&lt;/code&gt;, which sends the player back to the MainMenu map when he is killed by the snakes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;BasePointDestroyed()&lt;/code&gt;, which sends the player back to the MainMenu map when the base is destroyed by the snakes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;PlayerWon()&lt;/code&gt;, which sends the player back to the MainMenu map when he wins.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:center;&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.desert-defender.com/images/2025-03-15_19h03_16.png&#34; alt=&#34;Image Description&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>21 - Show, hide and switch equipped weapon actions and AnimBP</title>
      <link>https://blog.desert-defender.com/posts/21---show-hide-and-switch-equipped-weapon-actions-and-animbp/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.desert-defender.com/posts/21---show-hide-and-switch-equipped-weapon-actions-and-animbp/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have already implemented the ability for the coyote to pick up a weapon. When he does, he can no longer walk on all fours, and his &lt;code&gt;MaxWalk&lt;/code&gt; speed is reduced. This makes it harder to escape from the snakes chasing the player, and it leaves only a short window to benefit from the increased speed before picking up a weapon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To offer better gameplay, I have had the idea from the very beginning to allow the player to holster or put away the weapon and return to an unequipped state. The player would then be able to take the weapon from coyote back to shoot again, or switch weapons if a secondary weapon is equipped. As in a game like Apex Legends, I wanted to separate the controls for these actions: one key to show or hide the weapon, and the mouse wheel to switch between weapons.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>20 - Thinking on the game loop and starting the UI</title>
      <link>https://blog.desert-defender.com/posts/20---thinking-on-the-game-loop-and-starting-the-ui/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.desert-defender.com/posts/20---thinking-on-the-game-loop-and-starting-the-ui/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So far, I have been working on the game without taking the time to write down the logic of the game loop. But without it, it is not possible to start working on the &lt;code&gt;GameState&lt;/code&gt; or on the UI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I started by drawing a diagram with a basic color scheme: white background means I am sure about the step, yellow means it will be in the game but I don&amp;rsquo;t know exactly how it will be setup and red means that I am not sure about the step so it is not a priority as this point. For exemple in the picture bellow, working on a story introduction video or on some kind of items store does not make any sense for the moment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>19 - Unsyncing ennemies animations on spawn</title>
      <link>https://blog.desert-defender.com/posts/19---unsyncing-ennemies-animations-on-spawn/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.desert-defender.com/posts/19---unsyncing-ennemies-animations-on-spawn/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;From the start, I had a problem with the snakes and their animations: they were all synchronized with each other. This made their movement very unnatural.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To remedy this, I decided to get around it with the simplest possible solution: add a small delay between each snake spawn. I divided the existant &lt;code&gt;SpawnPoint&lt;/code&gt; &lt;code&gt;SpawnActor&lt;/code&gt; function to make it more readable and now the loop adds a small random delay between every spawn.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>18 - Creating the TinyTown map</title>
      <link>https://blog.desert-defender.com/posts/18---creating-the-tinytown-map/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.desert-defender.com/posts/18---creating-the-tinytown-map/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Until now, I had only a test map with a basic terrain so I decided to spend some time on level design. I started by drafting a map of a small town blocked in a valley by a mountain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My idea was to create a map with 3 attack paths for the snakes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One road from the north passing under a railway acting as a barrier for the player&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One canyon coming to the east&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One road coming from the west&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:center;&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.desert-defender.com/images/Pasted%20image%2020250220142629.png&#34; alt=&#34;Image Description&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>25 - Terrain material V2, changing light again, trusting Nanite and Lumen for rendering settings</title>
      <link>https://blog.desert-defender.com/posts/25---terrain-material-v2-changing-light-again-trusting-nanite-and-lumen-for-rendering-settings/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.desert-defender.com/posts/25---terrain-material-v2-changing-light-again-trusting-nanite-and-lumen-for-rendering-settings/</guid>
      
      <description></description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2 - Creating a mesh in blender, creating animations for idle, walk and jump</title>
      <link>https://blog.desert-defender.com/posts/2---creating-a-mesh-in-blender-creating-animations-for-idle-walk-and-jump/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.desert-defender.com/posts/2---creating-a-mesh-in-blender-creating-animations-for-idle-walk-and-jump/</guid>
      
      <description></description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1 - Project setup</title>
      <link>https://blog.desert-defender.com/posts/1---project-setup/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.desert-defender.com/posts/1---project-setup/</guid>
      
      <description></description>
      
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
